So, has everybody heard of CRISPR?
هل سمعتم من قبل بـ: كريسبر؟
I would be shocked if you hadn't.
سأصدم إن لم تفعلوا.
This is a technology -- it's for genome editing --
إنها تقنية -- تتعلق بتعديل الجينوم --
and it's so versatile and so controversial
وهي جد متشعبة ومثيرة للجدل
that it's sparking all sorts of really interesting conversations.
لدرجة إشعالها فتيل العديد من التساؤلات المثيرة للاهتمام.
Should we bring back the woolly mammoth?
مثل: هل علينا إحياء الماموث الصوفي؟
Should we edit a human embryo?
هل علينا تعديل الجنين البشري؟
And my personal favorite:
والمفضل لدي:
How can we justify wiping out an entire species
كيف يمكننا تبرير القضاء على نوع بالكامل
that we consider harmful to humans
من على وجه الأرض
off the face of the Earth,
لاعتبارنا إياه مضراً للبشر،
using this technology?
باستعمال هذه التقنية؟
This type of science is moving much faster
إن هذا النوع من التقنية يتطور بشكل سريع جداً
than the regulatory mechanisms that govern it.
بالمقارنة مع الآليات التنظيمية التي تسيرها.
And so, for the past six years,
وعليه، منذ السنوات الست الماضية،
I've made it my personal mission
أصبحت مهمتي الشخصية
to make sure that as many people as possible understand
هي التأكد من تعريف أكبر عدد ممكن من الناس
these types of technologies and their implications.
بهذا النوع من التقنيات ومجالات تطبيقها.
Now, CRISPR has been the subject of a huge media hype,
لقد شكلت كريسبر مؤخراً مادة دسمة للإعلام،
and the words that are used most often are "easy" and "cheap."
والكلمتين الأكثر استخداماً في وصفها هما "سهلة" و"رخيصة."
So what I want to do is drill down a little bit deeper
أما أنا فأود التعمّق بالأمر أكثر
and look into some of the myths and the realities around CRISPR.
والإطلاع على بعض الخرافات والحقائق المتعلقة بالكريسبر.
If you're trying to CRISPR a genome,
إن أردتم تطبيق كريسبر على الجينوم،
the first thing that you have to do is damage the DNA.
فإن أول ما عليكم فعله هو إتلاف الحمض النووي.
The damage comes in the form of a double-strand break
ويكون الإتلاف على شكل كسر مزدوج في السلستين
through the double helix.
وسط الحلزون المزدوج.
And then the cellular repair processes kick in,
لتبدأ بعدها عمليات الإصلاح الخلوي،
and then we convince those repair processes
فنُحدث عمليات الإصلاح تلك
to make the edit that we want,
بإجراء التعديل الذي نريده،
and not a natural edit.
وليس التعديل الطبيعي.
That's how it works.
وهذا يوضح كيف يتم الأمر.
It's a two-part system.
إنه نظام من قسمين.
You've got a Cas9 protein and something called a guide RNA.
عليكم الحصول على بروتين كاس9 وما يسمى بالحمض النووي الريبوزي الموجه.
I like to think of it as a guided missile.
وأحب تخيله كصاروخ موجه.
So the Cas9 -- I love to anthropomorphize --
إذاً، بروتين كاس9 -- أحب تجسيم الأشياء --
so the Cas9 is kind of this Pac-Man thing
إذا، بروتين كاس9 هو مثل باك مان
that wants to chew DNA,
هدفه هو التهام الحمض النووي،
and the guide RNA is the leash that's keeping it out of the genome
في حين أن الحمض النووي الريبوزي الموجه هو الحائل الذي يتركه خارج الجينوم
until it finds the exact spot where it matches.
إلى أن يجد المكان المناسب له.
And the combination of those two is called CRISPR.
والجمع بين هذين الأمرين يدعى بـ: كريسبر.
It's a system that we stole
وهو نظام سرقناه
from an ancient, ancient bacterial immune system.
من نظام مناعي بكتيري ضارب في القدم.
The part that's amazing about it is that the guide RNA,
والأمر المدهش حيال الحمض النووي الريبوزي الموجه،
only 20 letters of it,
هو أنه نظام يعمل
are what target the system.
بـ 20 حرف فقط.
This is really easy to design,
وهذا يسهل عملية تصميمه،
and it's really cheap to buy.
وثمنه رخيص جداً.
So that's the part that is modular in the system;
إنه الجزء الوحيد القابل للتركيب في النظام؛
everything else stays the same.
وما سواه يظل كما هو.
This makes it a remarkably easy and powerful system to use.
وهذا يجعل منه نظاماً رائعاً وقوياً للاستخدام.
The guide RNA and the Cas9 protein complex together
حيث يجتمع الحمض النووي الريبوزي الموجه وبروتين كاس9 معاً
go bouncing along the genome,
ويتنقلان داخل الجينوم،
and when they find a spot where the guide RNA matches,
وعندما يجدان المكان المناسب للحمض النووي الريبوزي الموجه،
then it inserts between the two strands of the double helix,
يتخذ مكانه بين سلسلتي الحلزون المزدوج،
it rips them apart,
فيفصل بينهما،
that triggers the Cas9 protein to cut,
مما يدفع بروتين كاس9 إلى القطع،
and all of a sudden,
وفجأة،
you've got a cell that's in total panic
تصبح لديكم خلية في حالة فزع
because now it's got a piece of DNA that's broken.
لأن قطعة من حمضها النووي قد كسرت.
What does it do?
فما الذي تفعله؟
It calls its first responders.
تقوم باستدعاء أسرع مسعفيها.
There are two major repair pathways.
هناك طريقتين رئيسيتين للإصلاح.
The first just takes the DNA and shoves the two pieces back together.
الأولى، أخذ الحمض النووي وإعادة وصل القطعتين معاً،
This isn't a very efficient system,
وهو نظام غير فعال بما يكفي،
because what happens is sometimes a base drops out
لأنه يقع أحياناً أن يُسقِط قاعدة
or a base is added.
أو يضيف أخرى.
It's an OK way to maybe, like, knock out a gene,
وربما تكون طريقة مقبولة للقضاء على مورثة ما،
but it's not the way that we really want to do genome editing.
لكنها ليست الطريقة التي نريدها بالفعل من أجل تعديل الجينوم.
The second repair pathway is a lot more interesting.
وطريقة الإصلاح الثانية هي أكثر إثارة للاهتمام.
In this repair pathway,
في هذه الطريقة،
it takes a homologous piece of DNA.
تستعمل قطع متماثلة من الحمض النووي.
And now mind you, in a diploid organism like people,
في كائن ثنائي الصيغة الصبغية كالبشر،
we've got one copy of our genome from our mom and one from our dad,
نحصل على نسخة من الجينوم من أمهاتنا وأخرى من آبائنا،
so if one gets damaged,
بحيث إن تضررت إحداها،
it can use the other chromosome to repair it.
يمكن استخدام الصبغي الآخر لإصلاحها.
So that's where this comes from.
وبذلك يتم الإصلاح.
The repair is made,
بإتمام الإصلاح،
and now the genome is safe again.
يكون الجينوم آمناً مرة أخرى.
The way that we can hijack this
الشكل الذي يمكن به استغلال ذلك
is we can feed it a false piece of DNA,
هو تزويده بقطعة خاطئة من الحمض النووي،
a piece that has homology on both ends
قطعة مماثلة عند طرفيها
but is different in the middle.
لكنها مختلفة في الوسط.
So now, you can put whatever you want in the center
لقد أصبح بإمكانكم وضع كل ما تريدون في الوسط
and the cell gets fooled.
فتنخدع الخلية.
So you can change a letter,
يمكنكم مثلا تغيير حرف ما،
you can take letters out,
أو حتى حذفه،
but most importantly, you can stuff new DNA in,
ولكن الأهم هو أنه يمكنكم ملؤها بحمض نووي جديد،
kind of like a Trojan horse.
كنوع من حصان طروادة.
CRISPR is going to be amazing,
سيكون كريسبر تقنية مدهشة،
in terms of the number of different scientific advances
من حيث عدد القفزات العلمية المختلفة
that it's going to catalyze.
التي سيكون له الفضل في تحفيزها.
The thing that's special about it is this modular targeting system.
والميزة الخاصة به هو نظام استهداف الوحدات.
I mean, we've been shoving DNA into organisms for years, right?
أقصد أننا نحشر الحمض النووي في الكائنات منذ سنوات، صحيح؟
But because of the modular targeting system,
لكن بفضل نظام استهداف الوحدات،
we can actually put it exactly where we want it.
يمكننا الآن وضعه حيث نريد بالضبط.
The thing is that there's a lot of talk about it being cheap
هناك الكثير من الأحاديث كونه رخيص الثمن
and it being easy.
وسهل الحصول عليه.
And I run a community lab.
وبما أني أدير مختبر عمومي،
I'm starting to get emails from people that say stuff like,
بدأت تصلني رسائل إلكترونية من أشخاص يطلبون أموراً مثل،
"Hey, can I come to your open night
"مرحبا، هل يمكنني خلال تنظيمكم للأبواب المفتوحة
and, like, maybe use CRISPR and engineer my genome?"
أن أستعمل، ربما، كريسبر لتعديل جيناتي؟"
(Laugher)
(ضحك)
Like, seriously.
فكنت أندهش!
I'm, "No, you can't."
فأجبت: "لا، لا يمكنك ذلك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"But I've heard it's cheap. I've heard it's easy."
"لكني سمعت أنه رخيص وسهل الحصول عليه."
We're going to explore that a little bit.
سنتحدث قليلاً عن هذا الأمر.
So, how cheap is it?
إلى أي حد هو رخيص؟
Yeah, it is cheap in comparison.
نعم، هو رخيص بالمقارنة.
It's going to take the cost of the average materials for an experiment
لأنه سيخفض تكلفة متوسط الأدوات اللازمة لتجربة ما
from thousands of dollars to hundreds of dollars,
من آلاف الدولارات إلى المئات فقط،
and it cuts the time a lot, too.
كما أنه يختصر الوقت كثيراً أيضاً.
It can cut it from weeks to days.
بحيث يختصره من أسابيع إلى أيام.
That's great.
وهذا عظيم.
You still need a professional lab to do the work in;
لكن ستظلون بحاجة إلى مختبر محترف لإنجاز العمل؛
you're not going to do anything meaningful outside of a professional lab.
فلا يمكنكم القيام بأي شيء ذو أهمية دون مختبر محترف.
I mean, don't listen to anyone who says
وأعني، لا تستمعوا إلى أي أحد يدعي
you can do this sort of stuff on your kitchen table.
بأنه يمكنكم القيام بشيء مثل هذا على طاولة مطبخكم.
It's really not easy to do this kind of work.
فالأمر ليس بالسهل للقيام بهذا النوع من العمل،
Not to mention, there's a patent battle going on,
ناهيك عن معركة براءة الإختراع الدائرة حوله،
so even if you do invent something,
وعليه حتى وإن اخترعت شيئاً ما.
the Broad Institute and UC Berkeley are in this incredible patent battle.
فإن معهد برود وجامعة كاليفورنيا في بركلي يخوضان معركة براءات اختراع مدهشة.
It's really fascinating to watch it happen,
ومن المدهش حقاً متابعة ما يقع،
because they're accusing each other of fraudulent claims
لأنهما يتهمان بعضهما بالإدعاءات الاحتيالية
and then they've got people saying,
ولديهم أشخاص يقولون،
"Oh, well, I signed my notebook here or there."
"أوه، حسناً، لقد وقعت ملاحظاتي هنا أو هناك."
This isn't going to be settled for years.
وهذا الأمر لن يحل قبل سنوات.
And when it is,
وعندما يصلان إلى حل،
you can bet you're going to pay someone a really hefty licensing fee
فتوقعوا أنكم ستدفعون لأحدهم رسوم ترخيص جد ضخمة
in order to use this stuff.
لاستخدام هذه الأشياء.
So, is it really cheap?
فهل هي رخيصة؟
Well, it's cheap if you're doing basic research and you've got a lab.
حسنا، ستكون كذلك إن كنتم تقومون بأبحاث أساسية ولديكم مختبر.
How about easy? Let's look at that claim.
وماذا عن سهولته؟ دعونا نتحدث عن هذا الإدعاء.
The devil is always in the details.
الشيطان يكمن في التفاصيل.
We don't really know that much about cells.
نحن لا نملك معرفة كافية بالخلايا.
They're still kind of black boxes.
فهي ما زالت كنوع من العلب السوداء.
For example, we don't know why some guide RNAs work really well
مثلاً، نحن لا نعرف لماذا تعمل بعض الأحماض النووية الريبوزية بشكل جيد
and some guide RNAs don't.
وأخرى لا.
We don't know why some cells want to do one repair pathway
ولا نعلم لما تفضل بعض الخلايا اتباع طريقة إصلاح معينة
and some cells would rather do the other.
في حين تتبع أخرى طريقة مغايرة.
And besides that,
وبالإضافة إلى ذلك،
there's the whole problem of getting the system into the cell
هناك مشكلة دمج النظام في الخلية
in the first place.
في المقام الأول.
In a petri dish, that's not that hard,
فمن السهل وضعه بطبق بتري،
but if you're trying to do it on a whole organism,
لكن إن حاولتم ذلك داخل كائن حي،
it gets really tricky.
فإن الأمر أكثر صعوبة.
It's OK if you use something like blood or bone marrow --
قد يكون الأمر أسهل إن استخدمتم مثلاً الدم أو نخاع العظام --
those are the targets of a lot of research now.
وهما حالياً موضوعان للكثير من البحوث.
There was a great story of some little girl
هناك قصة رائعة عن طفلة صغيرة
who they saved from leukemia
أنقذت من سرطان الدم
by taking the blood out, editing it, and putting it back
عن طريق أخذ دمها بالكامل وتعديله ثم إعادته
with a precursor of CRISPR.
بواسطة مركب طليعي لكريسبر.
And this is a line of research that people are going to do.
وهذا هو المنحى البحثي الذي سيتخذه الباحثون.
But right now, if you want to get into the whole body,
لكن حالياً، إن أردتم الدخول إلى الجسم بالكامل،
you're probably going to have to use a virus.
فعلى الأرجح سيتوجب عليكم استعمال الفيروسات.
So you take the virus, you put the CRISPR into it,
بحيث تأخذون الفيروس وتضعون كريسبر داخله،
you let the virus infect the cell.
وتتركون الفيروس يصيب الخلية.
But now you've got this virus in there,
لكن مع وصول الفيروس إلى الخلية،
and we don't know what the long-term effects of that are.
فإننا لا نعرف ما هي آثاره على المدى البعيد.
Plus, CRISPR has some off-target effects,
كما أن لكريسبر آثار جانبية،
a very small percentage, but they're still there.
بنسبة ضئيلة جداً، لكنها موجودة.
What's going to happen over time with that?
فما الذي سيقع مع مرور الوقت؟
These are not trivial questions,
وهذه ليست تساؤلات بسيطة،
and there are scientists that are trying to solve them,
وهناك علماء يحاولون الإجابة عنها،
and they will eventually, hopefully, be solved.
ونأمل أن تحل في نهاية المطاف.
But it ain't plug-and-play, not by a long shot.
لكن الأمر ليس بسحر، وسيتطلب وقتاً طويلاً.
So: Is it really easy?
إذاً، هل هو سهل حقاً؟
Well, if you spend a few years working it out in your particular system,
حسناً، إن قضيتم بضع سنوات تعملون على الأمر في نظامكم الخاص،
yes, it is.
فالأمر سهل.
Now the other thing is,
أما الأمر الآخر فهو
we don't really know that much about how to make a particular thing happen
كوننا لا نعرف ما يكفي حول كيفية جعل أمر معين يقع
by changing particular spots in the genome.
من خلال تغيير نقاط معينة في الجينوم.
We're a long way away from figuring out
فما نزال بعيدين كل البعد عن معرفة
how to give a pig wings, for example.
مثلاً، كيف نعطي للخنزير جناحين.
Or even an extra leg -- I'd settle for an extra leg.
أو نزوده برجل إضافية -- كنت سأختار الرجل الإضافية.
That would be kind of cool, right?
كان ذلك سيكون مثيراً، صحيح؟
But what is happening
لكن ما يحدث حالياً
is that CRISPR is being used by thousands and thousands of scientists
هو أن كريسبر يستخدم من قبل الآلاف من العلماء
to do really, really important work,
للقيام بأعمال مهمة جداً،
like making better models of diseases in animals, for example,
مثل إنشاء نماذج أفضل للأمراض في الحيوانات،
or for taking pathways that produce valuable chemicals
أو طرق أفضل لإنتاج مواد كيميائية مفيدة
and getting them into industrial production in fermentation vats,
واستعمالها في الإنتاج الصناعي بخزانات التخمير،
or even doing really basic research on what genes do.
أو حتى استعمالها في الأبحاث الأساسية حول عمل الجينات.
This is the story of CRISPR we should be telling,
هذه هي القصة التي ينبغي أن نحكيها عن كريسبر،
and I don't like it that the flashier aspects of it
ولا أحب أن تطغى عليها الجوانب المادية
are drowning all of this out.
بدلاً من الإطار الذي تحدثنا عنه.
Lots of scientists did a lot of work to make CRISPR happen,
فالعديد من العلماء يقومون بعمل جبار لإخراج كريسبر إلى الوجود،
and what's interesting to me
والمثير للاهتمام بالنسبة لي
is that these scientists are being supported by our society.
هو الدعم الذي يقدمه مجتمعنا لأولئك العلماء.
Think about it.
فكروا في الأمر.
We've got an infrastructure that allows a certain percentage of people
لدينا بينة تحتية تساعد نسبة معينة من الناس
to spend all their time doing research.
على قضاء كامل وقتهم في البحث العلمي.
That makes us all the inventors of CRISPR,
وهذا يجعلنا جميعاً مخترعين لكريسبر،
and I would say that makes us all the shepherds of CRISPR.
بل أود القول بأن ذلك يجعلنا جميعاً رعاةً لتقنية كريسبر.
We all have a responsibility.
ونتحمل جميعاً المسؤولية.
So I would urge you to really learn about these types of technologies,
لذا أحثكم بشدة للتعرف على هذا النوع من التقنيات،
because, really, only in that way
لأنه بالفعل هذه هي الطريقة الوحيدة
are we going to be able to guide the development of these technologies,
التي ستأهلنا لتوجيه تطور هذه التقنيات،
the use of these technologies
وكيفية استعمالها
and make sure that, in the end, it's a positive outcome --
والتأكد من أنه في نهاية المطاف، سنحصل على نتيجة إيجابية --
for both the planet and for us.
سواء بالنسبة لكوكبنا أو بالنسبة لنا.
Thanks.
شكرا جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)